Toni Morrison Papers,1908-2017: Finding Aid C1491
Manuscripts Division
Toni Morrison Papers
1970-2015
1908-2017
Manuscripts Division
Princeton University. Library. Special Collections
Morrison, Toni
C1491
337 boxes
16 items
Toni Morrison (born Chloe Ardelia Wofford, 1931-2019) was a Nobel prize-winning American author, editor, and Professor Emeritus at Princeton University. The material described in this finding aid consists of manuscripts, drafts, galleys, and proofs of Morrison's novels and other writings; personal correspondence; editorial files relating to Morrison's work at Random House and later publication of two posthumous works by Toni Cade Bambara; academic and teaching files, particularly pertaining to SUNY Albany and Princeton University; working files; press clippings; published books, photographs, audiovisual materials, and awards and memorabilia.
Scope and Contents
The material described in this finding aid consists of manuscripts, drafts, galleys, and proofs of Morrison's novels and other writings; personal correspondence; editorial files relating to Morrison's work at Random House and later publication of two posthumous works by Toni Cade Bambara; academic and teaching files, particularly pertaining to SUNY Albany and Princeton University; working files; press clippings; published books; photographs; audiovisual materials; and awards and memorabilia.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into the following series:
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research. Toni Morrison's manuscript material, including drafts, typescripts, galleys, and proofs found in boxes 1-11; 13-19; 22-29; 32-47; 50-56; 59-62; and 64-66 are available only via digital access in the reading room. Material in boxes 280-291; 305-308; 310-318; 320; 323; and 325 will also be available only via digital access in the reading room pending digitization. A small amount of material is temporarily restricted at the request of the collection creator or due to the presence of personally identifiable or other legally protected information. For preservation reasons, physical access to original audio and visual media in a variety of magnetic and optic formats is restricted.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Some material in this collection, particularly found in the Writings and Correspondence series, was damaged by the fire that destroyed Morrison's upstate New York home in 1993. Damage ranges from charred edges to pages missing significant portions or rendered illegible.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchase, 2009 (AM 2015-62), with accruals in 2015-2017: AM 2015-74, AM 2015-89, AM 2015-98, AM 2017-6, AM 2017-128, AM 2018-33, and AM 2018-78.
Appraisal
Some floppy disks were deaccessioned after imaging due to a lack of archival value. Duplicate papers and audiovisual materials were removed from the collection.
Related Materials
Other materials relating to Toni Morrison's work at Random House may be found in the Random House records at Columbia University's Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
Original drafts of Toni Cade Bambara's writings and related materials may be found in the Spelman College Archives.
A number of recordings of PEN American Center events in which Toni Morrison participated can be found in the PEN American Center Records (C0760). Online access to these recordings is available through the PEN America Digital Archive site.
Biographical / Historical
Toni Morrison was born Chloe Ardelia Wofford in Lorain, Ohio in 1931. She attended Howard University, graduating in 1953 with a degree in English, then received an MA in literature from Cornell University in 1955.
After a brief teaching stint at Texas Southern University, Morrison returned to teach at Howard in 1957. There, she married architect Harold Morrison, with whom she had two sons, Harold Ford Morrison (born 1961) and Slade Kevin Morrison (1964-2010). The two divorced around the time of Slade's birth, after which Morrison began working as a textbook editor for a division of Random House based in Syracuse, NY. In 1967, Morrison was promoted to senior editor and moved to New York City, where she worked with a number of emerging influential African-American writers, including Toni Cade Bambara, Angela Davis, Henry Dumas, and Gayl Jones, in addition to editing The Black Book (1974), a compilation of African-American historical documents.
Morrison's first novel, The Bluest Eye, was published in 1970. She has published a total of eleven novels to date, winning numerous literary and cultural awards including the Pulitzer Prize for Fiction for Beloved in 1988, the Nobel Prize in Literature in 1993, the National Humanities Medal in 2000, and the Presidential Medal of Freedom in 2012. In addition to her novels, Morrison has written non-fiction, poetry, children's literature (in collaboration with her son Slade), and dramatic works.
In 1983, she left her position at Random House to concentrate on writing and teaching, serving as the Albert Schweitzer Professor of the Humanities at SUNY Albany from 1984-1989, then the Robert E. Goheen Professor in the Council of the Humanities at Princeton University until her retirement in 2006. During this time, she taught classes in creative writing, African-American studies, and, at Princeton, developed the interdisciplinary Atelier program. She has also served as a visiting professor and lecturer at numerous institutions, including Yale University, the University of Michigan, the University of Chicago, and Harvard University.
Morrison lived in Grand View-on-Hudson in New York until her death in 2019 at age 88.
Biographical / Historical
Toni Morrison was born Chloe Ardelia Wofford in Lorain, Ohio in 1931. She attended Howard University, graduating in 1953 with a degree in English, then received an MA in literature from Cornell University in 1955.
After a brief teaching stint at Texas Southern University, Morrison returned to teach at Howard in 1957. There, she married architect Harold Morrison, with whom she had two sons, Harold Ford Morrison (born 1961) and Slade Kevin Morrison (1964-2010). The two divorced around the time of Slade's birth, after which Morrison began working as a textbook editor for a division of Random House based in Syracuse, NY. In 1967, Morrison was promoted to senior editor and moved to New York City, where she worked with a number of emerging influential African-American writers, including Toni Cade Bambara, Angela Davis, Henry Dumas, and Gayl Jones, in addition to editing The Black Book (1974), a compilation of African-American historical documents.
Morrison's first novel, The Bluest Eye, was published in 1970. She has published a total of eleven novels to date, winning numerous literary and cultural awards including the Pulitzer Prize for Fiction for Beloved in 1988, the Nobel Prize in Literature in 1993, the National Humanities Medal in 2000, and the Presidential Medal of Freedom in 2012. In addition to her novels, Morrison has written non-fiction, poetry, children's literature (in collaboration with her son Slade), and dramatic works.
In 1983, she left her position at Random House to concentrate on writing and teaching, serving as the Albert Schweitzer Professor of the Humanities at SUNY Albany from 1984-1989, then the Robert E. Goheen Professor in the Council of the Humanities at Princeton University until her retirement in 2006. During this time, she taught classes in creative writing, African-American studies, and, at Princeton, developed the interdisciplinary Atelier program. She has also served as a visiting professor and lecturer at numerous institutions, including Yale University, the University of Michigan, the University of Chicago, and Harvard University.
Morrison lived in Grand View-on-Hudson in New York until her death in 2019 at age 88.
African American authors -- 20th century -- Sources.; Authors, American -- 20th century -- Sources.; Novelists.; Nobel Prize winners.; Women Nobel Prize winners.; Correspondence.; Fan mail.; Interviews.; Proofs (printed matter).; Typescripts.; Photographs.
- Writings, 1917-2017 April 11; 94 boxes; 16 items
  Conditions Governing Access
  The collection is open for research. Toni Morrison's manuscript material, including drafts, typescripts, galleys, and proofs found in boxes 1-11; 13-19; 22-29; 32-47; 50-56; 59-62; and 64-66 are available only via digital access in the reading room. Material in boxes 280-291; 305-308; 310-318; 320; 323; and 325 will also be available only via digital access in the reading room pending digitization. A small amount of material is temporarily restricted at the request of the collection creator or due to the presence of personally identifiable or other legally protected information. For preservation reasons, physical access to original audio and visual media in a variety of magnetic and optic formats is restricted.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged into subseries by genre.
  Scope and Contents
  Consists of research material, notes, outlines, drafts, galleys, and proofs. Yellow legal notepads contain notes, early draft material, and inserts for later typed and printed versions. Notepads are identified by their first lines, though a single notepad may contain a variety of material, including material relating to other works, correspondence drafts, and other unrelated notes. Corrected typescript and printout drafts often show significant revisions. Material from various stages of the publication process is present, including setting copies with copy-editor's and typesetter's marks, galleys, page proofs, F&Gs (folded-and-gathered pages, in signatures but not yet bound), blueline proofs ("confirmation blues"), advance copies (bound uncorrected proofs, pre-publication, often used for book reviewers) and production/design material with page and dust-jacket samples. Page numbers are noted for paginated material.
  - Novels, 1917-2015; 68 boxes
    Arranged chronologically by publication date.
    All of Morrison's novels except Song of Solomon are represented (this material was likely destroyed in the 1993 fire).
    - The Bluest Eye, 1970; 3 boxes
      For the short story "Two of Eve's," an early version of The Bluest Eye, see Short Fiction.
      - Outlines and Notes, undated; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 1)
        Toni Morrison has required the Library to make surrogate copies of all of her manuscripts (including typescripts and proofs) and diaries (appointment books), including but not restricted to those damaged by fire in 1993. This is for conservation reasons, to prevent damage and deterioration by repeated use. Researchers are required to use digital surrogates in the reading room of the Special Collections.
    - Beloved, 1984-1999; 9 boxes
      Numbered drafts per original folder labels. Born-digital drafts are also present, see Floppy Disks.
      - Beloved Research Files, 1985-1986; 1 box
        Consists of research notes and photocopies of articles, book excerpts, and primary sources.
        - Smith, James McCune, 1985 February; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Paradise, 1971 June-2014; 12 boxes
      Born-digital drafts are also present, see Floppy Disks.
      - "1963/Soane's abortion...", undated; 1 folder Notepad. (Box 32, Folder 8)
- Working Files, 1955-2018; 68 boxes
  This series is arranged into subseries following the original grouping of material. The Office Working Files are divided into roughly chronological files groupings, with Office Working Files I being the oldest and Office Working Files IV being the most recent, although there is considerable overlap between II and III. The Additional Working Files subseries includes additional materials received after the bulk of the papers were arranged.
  This series consists of files maintained by Morrison and her administrative assistants, including Ronaline Saunders, Rene Boatman, and John Hoppenthaler. The first subseries of files concern Morrison's book and writings projects, and include correspondence with editors, publishers, and translators, as well as publicity tour schedules and related material. The office files, maintained at Morrison's offices at SUNY Albany and later Princeton University, document Morrison's activities, including awards, conferences, lectures, interviews, etc., throughout her career as a public figure. The office files also include subject files pertaining to her publishers, literary agency, various professional organizations, and individuals; letterbooks of administrative correspondence sent by Morrison and her assistants, various requests received, and fan mail. The files from Morrison's home office are similar in content to the office working files, but are the primary location of book contracts and royalty statements.
  - Additional Working Files, 1992-2018; 4 boxes
    Includes additional working files received after the bulk of the papers were arranged.
    Materials are arranged in the order in which they were received.
    - Fan Mail, 1992-2018; 3 boxes
      Includes some ephemeral items as well as theses and dissertations sent to Morrison.
      - Fan Mail, 1992-2018; 2 folders (Box 330, Folder 5-6)
- Audiovisual Materials, 1972-2014 February 22; 19 boxes
  For preservation reasons, physical access to original audio and visual media in a variety of magnetic and optic formats is restricted. The Special Collections does not have playback equipment and facilities, and all original media, especially in obsolete formats, must be digitally remastered or converted in accordance with prevailing preservation standards in order to be safely accessed. Subject to staffial approval, patrons may request duplicates of such original media, but will be responsible for both the cost of digital conversion and the cost of the duplicate, payable in advance. Public Services staff handles all such requests. Depending on the nature of the media, this process can take 4-6 weeks or longer.
  Includes digital photographs and audio and visual recordings of award ceremonies, lectures, and other events attended by Toni Morrison; radio and television programs in which she is interviewed or otherwise featured; and commercially-produced audiobooks of her work. Official Princeton University recordings featuring Toni Morrison can be found in University Archive's Broadcast Center Recordings: http://findingaids.princeton.edu/collections/AC362. Titles, dates, and other descriptive information of this material is taken from media markings on the case and labels and accompanying material if present, and may not match the content of the media.
  This material is grouped by type.
  - Awards, Lectures, Interviews, and Event Recordings, 1975 March 19-2013; 11 boxes
    - Birth of Black Cinema Symposium, 1988 November 17-19; 1 box 10 audio cassettes (Box 232)
      Sponsored by Toni Morrison, SUNY Albany